Everything I do, and everything I do professionally --
كل ما أقوم به، وكل ما أقوم به في حياتي العملية
my life -- has been shaped
حياتي كلها -- قد تشكلت بفعل
by seven years of work as a young man in Africa.
سبع سنوات عمل قضيتها في أفريقيا وأنا شاب.
From 1971 to 1977 --
من 1971 حتى 1977
I look young, but I'm not — (Laughter) --
أبدو شاباً لكن الأمر ليس كذلك (ضحك)
I worked in Zambia, Kenya, Ivory Coast, Algeria, Somalia,
لقد عملت في زامبيا وكينيا وساحل العاج والجزائر والصومال،
in projects of technical cooperation with African countries.
في مشاريع تعاون تقني مع بلدان أفريقيا.
I worked for an Italian NGO,
كنت أعمل لإحدى المنظمات غير الحكومية الإيطالية،
and every single project that we set up in Africa
و كل مشروع من المشاريع التي أقمناها في أفريقيا
failed.
قد باء بالفشل.
And I was distraught.
شعرت بخيبة شديدة.
I thought, age 21, that we Italians were good people
كنت أظن، وأنا في سن الواحد والعشرين، أننا، نحن الايطاليون، أهل خير وأناس طيبون
and we were doing good work in Africa.
وأننا نقوم بعمل جيد في أفريقيا
Instead, everything we touched we killed.
لكن بدلاً من ذلك، كنَّا نقتل كل ما نلمسه.
Our first project, the one that has inspired my first book,
مشروعنا الأول، الذي ألهمني لكتابة كتابي الأول،
"Ripples from the Zambezi,"
"تموجات نهر زامبيزي"
was a project where we Italians
كان مشروعاً حيث نحن الإيطاليون
decided to teach Zambian people how to grow food.
قررنا أن نعلّم أهل زامبيا كيفية إنتاج المحاصيل الزراعية
So we arrived there with Italian seeds in southern Zambia
وهكذا، وصلنا هناك مُحمَّلين ببذور إيطالية إلى جنوب زامبيا،
in this absolutely magnificent valley
إلى ذلك الوادي الرائع
going down to the Zambezi River,
المؤدي إلى نهر زامبيزي،
and we taught the local people how to grow Italian tomatoes
وعلّمنا السكان المحليين كيفية زراعة الطماطم الإيطالية
and zucchini and ...
والكوسة وغيرها...
And of course the local people had absolutely no interest
وبالطبع لم يكن للسكان المحليين أدنى اهتمام بذلك
in doing that, so we paid them to come and work,
لذلك وجب علينا أن ندفع لهم أجوراً حتى يأتوا و يعملوا
and sometimes they would show up. (Laughter)
وفعلا كانوا يأتون... في بعض الأحيان. (ضحك)
And we were amazed that the local people,
و كنا نستغرب لأمر السكان المحليين،
in such a fertile valley, would not have any agriculture.
الذين لا يزرعون في مثل هذا الوادي الخصب.
But instead of asking them how come they were not
لكن بدل أن نسألهم عن السبب الكامن وراء ذلك،
growing anything, we simply said, "Thank God we're here." (Laughter)
قلنا لهم ببساطة "اشكروا الله على مجيئنا" (ضحك)
"Just in the nick of time to save the Zambian people from starvation."
"وفي الوقت المناسب تماماً لإنقاذ الشعب الزامبي من الموت جوعا."
And of course, everything in Africa grew beautifully.
وبالطبع، كل شئ نما بشكل رائع في أفريقيا.
We had these magnificent tomatoes. In Italy, a tomato
لقد حصلنا على طماطم هائلة. في إيطاليا
would grow to this size. In Zambia, to this size.
تنمو الطماطم إلى هذا الحجم. أما في زامبيا فهي تنمو إلى هذا الحجم.
And we could not believe, and we were telling the Zambians,
وكان الأمر يذهلنا، وكنا نقول للزامبيين
"Look how easy agriculture is."
"أنظروا ما أسهل الفلاحة !"
When the tomatoes were nice and ripe and red,
لمَّا نضجت الطماطم واحمرّ لونها
overnight, some 200 hippos came out from the river
خرج من النهر قرابة مئتي فرس بحر، ودون سابق إنذار،
and they ate everything. (Laughter)
والتهمت كل شئ. (ضحك)
And we said to the Zambians, "My God, the hippos!"
فقلنا للزامبيين، "يا إلهي، أفراس النهر!"
And the Zambians said, "Yes, that's why we have no agriculture here." (Laughter)
حينها أجاب الزامبيون، "نعم، ولهذا السبب لايوجد زراعة في هذه المنطقة." (ضحك)
"Why didn't you tell us?""You never asked."
"ولكن لما لم تخبرونا من قبل؟" "لم تسألوننا عن ذلك."
I thought it was only us Italians blundering around Africa,
كنت أظن أننا فقط نحن الإيطاليون من نتصرف بحماقة في أفريقيا،
but then I saw what the Americans were doing,
ثم رأيت ما كان يصنعه الأمريكان،
what the English were doing, what the French were doing,
وما كان يصنعه الإنجليز والفرنسيين،
and after seeing what they were doing,
وبعد أن رأيت ما كانوا يقومون به،
I became quite proud of our project in Zambia.
أصبحت أفتخر بمشروعنا في زامبيا،
Because, you see, at least we fed the hippos.
لأننا، على الأقل، قد وفَّرنا بعض الغذاءِ لأفراس النهر
You should see the rubbish — (Applause) --
عليكم أن تروا النفاية (تصفيق)
You should see the rubbish that we have bestowed
عليكم أن تروا النفاية التي وهبناها
on unsuspecting African people.
للأفارقة المطمئنين.
You want to read the book,
إن أردت أن تقرأ كتاباً،
read "Dead Aid," by Dambisa Moyo,
فاقرأ كتاب "Dead Aid" لدامبيسا مويو،
Zambian woman economist.
خبيرة اقتصادية زامبية
The book was published in 2009.
الكتاب قد نُشر في عام 2009.
We Western donor countries have given the African continent
نحن كدول غربية متبرعة قد وهبنا للقارة الأفريقية ما يناهز
two trillion American dollars in the last 50 years.
ترليوني دولار خلال السنوات الخمسين الماضية.
I'm not going to tell you the damage that that money has done.
لن أذكر لكم مدى الضرر الذي أحدثه ذلك المال.
Just go and read her book.
كل ما قد أطلبه منكم هو أن تقرؤوا كتابها.
Read it from an African woman, the damage that we have done.
اطّلعوا، من خلال كتاب تلك المرأة الأفريقية، على الأذى الذي أحدثناه.
We Western people are imperialist, colonialist missionaries,
نحن الغربيون إمبرياليين، واستعماريين ومبشرين.
and there are only two ways we deal with people:
ولا نتعامل مع غيرنا إلا بطريقتين،
We either patronize them, or we are paternalistic.
نحن إما أن نكون أولياء عليهم، أو نتعامل معهم بشكل أبوي.
The two words come from the Latin root "pater,"
الكلمتان مشتقتان من الأصل اللاتيني "Pater"
which means "father."
ومعناه "أب".
But they mean two different things.
لكنهما تدلاّن على شيئين مختلفين.
Paternalistic, I treat anybody from a different culture
الرعاية الأبوية "Paternalistic"، أن أتعامل مع أي شخص ينتمي لثقافة مختلفة
as if they were my children. "I love you so much."
كما لو كان ابني. "أحبك كثيراً."
Patronizing, I treat everybody from another culture
الولاية، أن أتعامل مع أي شخص ينتمي لثقافة مختلفة
as if they were my servants.
كما لو كان خادماً عندي.
That's why the white people in Africa are called "bwana," boss.
لذلك يلقب البيض في أفريقيا ب"bwana"، كلمة معناها "الزعيم".
I was given a slap in the face reading a book,
تلقيت صفعة على الوجه من خلال قراءة لكتاب،
"Small is Beautiful," written by Schumacher, who said,
وهو كتاب "كل صغير جميل"، لكاتبه شوماخر، الذي قال:
above all in economic development, if people
قبل كل شئ، في مجال التنمية الإقتصادية، إن لم
do not wish to be helped, leave them alone.
يرغب الناس بالمساعدة، دعهم وشأنهم.
This should be the first principle of aid.
يجب أن يكون هذا أول مبادئ المساعدة.
The first principle of aid is respect.
أول مبدأ للمساعدة هو الاحترام.
This morning, the gentleman who opened this conference
هذا الصباح، قام الرجل الذي افتتح هذا المؤتمر
lay a stick on the floor, and said,
بوضع عصا على الأرض ثم قال،
"Can we -- can you imagine a city
" هل يمكننا تخيل مدينة
that is not neocolonial?"
ليست استعمارية جديدة؟"
I decided when I was 27 years old
عندما كنت في السابعة عشرة، قررت فقط
to only respond to people,
أن أستجيب للناس،
and I invented a system called Enterprise Facilitation,
وابتكرت نظام أسميته بـ تيسير المشاريع
where you never initiate anything,
حيث لا تبادر بأي شيء مطلقاً،
you never motivate anybody, but you become a servant
ولا تحفز أحداً، بل تصبح خادماً
of the local passion, the servant of local people
للشغف المحلي، خادماً للسكان المحليين
who have a dream to become a better person.
الذين يحلمون بأن يكونوا أناس أفضل.
So what you do -- you shut up.
فما تقوم به هو أن تصمت.
You never arrive in a community with any ideas,
لا ينبغي عليك أن تفد على مجتمع وتقدم أي أفكار
and you sit with the local people.
وأن تجلس مع السكان المحليين.
We don't work from offices.
نحن لا نعمل من المكاتب.
We meet at the cafe. We meet at the pub.
نلتقي في مقهى، أو في حانة.
We have zero infrastructure.
لا يوجد لدينا أي بنية أساسية.
And what we do, we become friends,
وما نقوم به، هو أن نكون أصدقاء،
and we find out what that person wants to do.
ونكتشف ماذا يريد أن يكون هذا الشخص.
The most important thing is passion.
الشيء الأهم هو الشغف.
You can give somebody an idea.
يمكنك أن تعرض فكرة على شخصٍ ما.
If that person doesn't want to do it,
إن لم يرغب هذا الشخص بتنفيذها،
what are you going to do?
ماذا عليك أن تفعل؟
The passion that the person has for her own growth
الشغف الذي يملكه هذه المرأة لنموّها الشخصي
is the most important thing.
هو الشئ الأهم.
The passion that that man has for his own personal growth
الشغف الذي يملكه هذا الرجل لنموّه الشخصي
And then we help them to go and find the knowledge,
ومن ثم نساعدهم ليكتشفوا المعرفة،
because nobody in the world can succeed alone.
لأنه لا يمكن لأي شخص في هذا العالم أن ينجح بمفرده.
The person with the idea may not have the knowledge,
من يملك فكرة قد لا يملك معرفة،
but the knowledge is available.
لكن المعرفة متوفرة.
So years and years ago, I had this idea:
لذا، منذ سنوات وسنوات سابقة توصلت لهذه الفكرة:
Why don't we, for once, instead of arriving in the community
لماذا نحن لا، لمرة واحدة، بدلاً من أن نأتي لمجتمع
to tell people what to do, why don't, for once,
لنملي عليهم مايفعلون، لماذا، ولمرة واحدة فقط،
listen to them? But not in community meetings.
لا نستمع لهم؟ لكن لا يكون ذلك في لقاءات المجتمع.
Let me tell you a secret.
دعني أخبرك سراً.
There is a problem with community meetings.
هناك مشكلة مع لقاءات المجتمع.
Entrepreneurs never come,
روّاد الأعمال لا يأتون إليها أبداً،
and they never tell you, in a public meeting,
ولا يخبرونك أبداً، في اجتماع عام،
what they want to do with their own money,
عن ماذا يريدون فعله بأموالهم،
what opportunity they have identified.
أو أي فرصة تعرفوا عليها.
So planning has this blind spot.
لهذا السبب، يعاني التخطيط من هذه النقطة العمياء.
The smartest people in your community you don't even know,
أذكى الأشخاص في مجتمعك لا تعرفهم،
because they don't come to your public meetings.
لأنهم لا يحضرون لاجتماعاتك العامة.
What we do, we work one-on-one,
ما نقوم به هو أننا نعمل فردياً،
and to work one-on-one, you have to create
ولكي تعمل بشكل فردي، عليك أن تُنشئ
a social infrastructure that doesn't exist.
بنية تحتية اجتماعية غير متوفرة.
You have to create a new profession.
عليك أن تُنشئ مهنة جديدة.
The profession is the family doctor of enterprise,
المهنة الجديدة هي طبيب العائلة الخاص بالمشروع
the family doctor of business, who sits with you
الطبيب الخاص بالمشروع التجاري، الذي يجلس معك
in your house, at your kitchen table, at the cafe,
في منزلك، على طاولة مطبخك، في المقهى،
and helps you find the resources to transform your passion
ليساعدك على إيجاد مصادر تعينك على تحويل شغفك
into a way to make a living.
إلى وسيلة تكسب بها عيشك.
I started this as a tryout in Esperance, in Western Australia.
بدأت ذلك كتجربة في اسبرانس في غرب استراليا.
I was a doing a Ph.D. at the time,
كنت أحضّر الدكتوراه في ذلك الوقت،
trying to go away from this patronizing bullshit
محاولة مني لأهرب من هذه الولاية الجوفاء
that we arrive and tell you what to do.
حيث نملي عليك ما تفعله.
And so what I did in Esperance that first year
ما فعلته في اسبرانس في السنة الأولى تلك
was to just walk the streets, and in three days
هو أني كنت أمشي في الشوارع، وخلال ثلاث أيام
I had my first client, and I helped this first guy
حصلت على عميلي الأول، وساعدت هذا الشاب الأول
who was smoking fish from a garage, was a Maori guy,
الذي كان يُدخن السمك من المرآب، كان من الشعب الماوري،
and I helped him to sell to the restaurant in Perth,
وساعدته ليبيع السمك في مطعم في مدينة بيرث
to get organized, and then the fishermen came to me to say,
ليعمل بشكل منظم، وبعدها أتي إلي صيادي السمك ليقولوا،
"You the guy who helped Maori? Can you help us?"
"هل أنت من ساعد ماوري؟ هل يمكنك مساعدتنا؟"
And I helped these five fishermen to work together
وساعدت أولئك الصيادين الخمسة ليعملوا معاً
and get this beautiful tuna not to the cannery in Albany
وينقلوا سمك التونا الجميل هذا ليس فقط إلى مصنع التعليب في ألباني
for 60 cents a kilo, but we found a way
مقابل ستين سنتاً للكيلو، بل وجدنا طريقة
to take the fish for sushi to Japan for 15 dollars a kilo,
لتصدير سمك السوشي لليابان مقابل 15 دولار للكيلو.
and the farmers came to talk to me, said,
ثم جاء الفلاحين ليتحدثوا معي قائلين:
"Hey, you helped them. Can you help us?"
"لقد قمت بمساعدتهم، هل يمكنك مساعدتنا؟"
In a year, I had 27 projects going on,
خلال سنة، عملت على 27 مشروع،
and the government came to see me to say,
وجائتني الحكومة لتقول:
"How can you do that?
"كيف يمكنك فعل هذا؟"
How can you do — ?" And I said, "I do something very, very, very difficult.
كيف يمكنك فعل ...؟" وقلت:"أقوم بعمل شيء صعب جداً جداً جداً.
I shut up, and listen to them." (Laughter)
اصمت، وانصت إليهم." (ضحك)
So — (Applause) —
لذا - (تصفيق)
So the government says, "Do it again." (Laughter)
تقول الحكومة، "افعلها مرة أخرى." (ضحك)
We've done it in 300 communities around the world.
قمنا بعمل ذلك في 300 مجتمع حول العالم.
We have helped to start 40,000 businesses.
قدمنا يد المساعدة لبدء 40.000 مشروع.
There is a new generation of entrepreneurs
يوجد جيل جديد من روّاد الأعمال
who are dying of solitude.
الذين يستميتون للتفرد.
Peter Drucker, one of the greatest management consultants in history,
بيتر دروكر، أحد أكبر المستشارين الإداريين في التاريخ،
died age 96, a few years ago.
مات منذ سنوات قليلة وهو في سن السادسة والتسعين.
Peter Drucker was a professor of philosophy
كان بيتر دروكر استاذاً للفلسفة
before becoming involved in business,
قبل أن ينخرط في مجال التجارة،
and this is what Peter Drucker says:
وهذا ماكان يقوله بيتر دروكر:
"Planning is actually incompatible
"التخطيط متعارض
with an entrepreneurial society and economy."
مع المجتمع الريادي والإقتصادي."
Planning is the kiss of death of entrepreneurship.
التخطيط هو قبلة موت ريادة الأعمال.
So now you're rebuilding Christchurch
أنت الآن تعيد بناء مدينة كريست تشرتش
without knowing what the smartest people in Christchurch
وأنت تجهل ماذا يريد أذكى الناس فيها
want to do with their own money and their own energy.
ماذا يريد القيام به بمالهم الخاص وطاقتهم الخاصة.
You have to learn how to get these people
عليك أن تعرف كيف تُحضر أولئك الأشخاص
to come and talk to you.
ليتحدثوا إليك.
You have to offer them confidentiality, privacy,
عليك أن تقدم لهم الثقة والخصوصية
you have to be fantastic at helping them,
عليك أن تساعدهم بشكل مبهر،
and then they will come, and they will come in droves.
وعندها فقط سيأتون إليك. أفواج كثيرة ستأتي إليك.
In a community of 10,000 people, we get 200 clients.
تقدم إلينا 200 عميل من مجتمع مكوّن من 10.000 شخص.
Can you imagine a community of 400,000 people,
هل يمكنك تخيّل مجتمع مكوّن من 400,000 شخص،
the intelligence and the passion?
الذكاء والشغف؟
Which presentation have you applauded the most this morning?
أي عرض هتفت له هذا الصباح؟
Local, passionate people. That's who you have applauded.
الناس المحليين المتحمسين. هم من هتفت لهم.
So what I'm saying is that
ما أقوله هو
entrepreneurship is where it's at.
ريادة الأعمال تجدها حيث ماتكون.
We are at the end of the first industrial revolution --
نحن على مشارف نهاية الثورة الصناعية الأولى --
nonrenewable fossil fuels, manufacturing --
الوقود الأحفوري الغير متجدد والصناعة التحويلية --
and all of a sudden, we have systems which are not sustainable.
وبشكل مفاجئ، تتوفر لدينا أنظمة غير مستدامة.
The internal combustion engine is not sustainable.
محرك الاحتراق الداخلي غير مستدام.
Freon way of maintaining things is not sustainable.
طريقة حفظ الأشياء بالفريون غير مستدامة.
What we have to look at is at how we
مايجب أن نهتم له هو كيف
feed, cure, educate, transport, communicate
نوفر الطعام، والعلاج، والتعليم، ووسائل النقل والاتصالات
for seven billion people in a sustainable way.
لسبعة مليار نسمة بطريقة مستدامة.
The technologies do not exist to do that.
لم تُوجد التقنيات لفعل ذلك.
Who is going to invent the technology
من سيبتكر التقنية
for the green revolution? Universities? Forget about it!
للثورة الخضراء؟ الجامعات؟ انسوا الأمر!
Government? Forget about it!
الحكومة؟ انسوا الأمر!
It will be entrepreneurs, and they're doing it now.
سيبتكرها روّاد الأعمال، وهم يفعلون ذلك الآن.
There's a lovely story that I read in a futurist magazine
هناك قصة جميلة قرأتها في مجلة تنبؤية
many, many years ago.
منذ عدة سنوات.
There was a group of experts who were invited
تمت دعوة مجموعة من الخبراء
to discuss the future of the city of New York in 1860.
لمناقشة مستقبل مدينة نيويورك في عام 1860.
And in 1860, this group of people came together,
وفي عام 1860، اجتمعت هذه المجموعة
and they all speculated about what would happen
وقاموا بتخمين ماذا سيحدث
to the city of New York in 100 years,
لمدينة نيويورك خلال مئة عام.
and the conclusion was unanimous:
وكانت النتيجة بالإجماع:
The city of New York would not exist in 100 years.
مدينة نيويورك لن تكون موجودة خلال مئة سنة.
Why? Because they looked at the curve and said,
لماذا؟ لأنهم نظروا إلى المنحنى وقالوا:
if the population keeps growing at this rate,
إذا استمر عدد السكان بالارتفاع بهذا المعدل،
to move the population of New York around,
سيحتاج سكان نيويورك إلى ست ملايين
they would have needed six million horses,
حصان كي يتمكنوا من التنقل.
and the manure created by six million horses
وسيكون التعامل مع روث هذا العدد الهائل
would be impossible to deal with.
من الخيول مستحيلاً.
They were already drowning in manure. (Laughter)
كانوا غارقين في الروث بالفعل. (ضحك)
So 1860, they are seeing this dirty technology
ففي عام 1860، كانوا يعتبرون ذلك تقنية قذرة
that is going to choke the life out of New York.
ستؤدي إلى خنق الحياة في مدينة نيويورك.
So what happens? In 40 years' time, in the year 1900,
فماذا حدث؟ خلال أربعين سنة، في عام 1900،
in the United States of America, there were 1,001
كان يوجد في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية 1,001
car manufacturing companies -- 1,001.
شركة لتصنيع السيارات -- 1,001.
The idea of finding a different technology
فكرة إيجاد تقنية جديدة
had absolutely taken over,
تم تبنيها حقاً.
and there were tiny, tiny little factories in backwaters.
وكان يوجد قليل من المصانع الصغيرة في الأماكن النائية.
Dearborn, Michigan. Henry Ford.
ديربورن، ميتشجان. هنري فورد.
However, there is a secret to work with entrepreneurs.
على أي حال، يوجد سر للعمل مع روّاد الأعمال.
First, you have to offer them confidentiality.
أولاً، عليك أن توفر لهم الثقة.
Otherwise they don't come and talk to you.
وإلا لن يأتوك ليتحدثوا إليك.
Then you have to offer them absolute, dedicated,
ثم عليك أن تقدم لهم خدمة جليلة
passionate service to them.
مطلقة ومتفانية.
And then you have to tell them the truth about entrepreneurship.
ثم عليك أن تخبرهم الحقيقة حول ريادة الأعمال.
The smallest company, the biggest company,
الشركات الصغرى، الشركات الكبرى
has to be capable of doing three things beautifully:
عليها أن تكون قادرة على فعل ثلاث أشياء بشكل رائع:
The product that you want to sell has to be fantastic,
على المنتج الذي توّد بيعه أن يكون مبهر،
you have to have fantastic marketing,
ينبغي أن تسوّقه بشكل رائع،
and you have to have tremendous financial management.
وعليك أن تملك إدارة مالية رائعة.
Guess what?
خمّنوا ماذا؟
We have never met a single human being
لم نلتقي أبداً بأحد
in the world who can make it, sell it and look after the money.
في العالم يمكنه فعل ذلك، يصنع المنتج، يبيعه ويحافظ على المال.
It doesn't exist.
لا يوجد هذا الشخص.
This person has never been born.
لم يُولد هذا الشخص.
We've done the research, and we have looked
أنهينا البحث، وقمنا بالنظر إلى
at the 100 iconic companies of the world --
100 شركة عالمية أيقونية --
Carnegie, Westinghouse, Edison, Ford,
كارنيجي، ويستسنجهاوس، إديسون، فورد
all the new companies, Google, Yahoo.
وكل الشركات الجديدة، قوقل، ياهو.
There's only one thing that all the successful companies
هناك صفة واحدة فقط مشتركة بين
in the world have in common, only one:
كل الشركات العالمية الناجحة، أمر واحد فقط:
None were started by one person.
لم تنشأ شركة بمجهود شخص واحد فقط.
Now we teach entrepreneurship to 16-year-olds
نقوم الآن بتدريس ريادة الأعمال لطلاب في سن السادسة عشرة
in Northumberland, and we start the class
في نورثمبرلاند، وبدأنا الفصل
by giving them the first two pages of Richard Branson's autobiography,
بإعطائهم أول صفحتين من سيرة ريتشارد برانسون الذاتية،
and the task of the 16-year-olds is to underline,
وكانت مهمّة أولئك الطلاب هو تحديد
in the first two pages of Richard Branson's autobiography
عدد المرات استخدم فيها ريتشارد كلمة "أنا"
how many times Richard uses the word "I"
في أول صفحتين من سيرته الذاتية
and how many times he uses the word "we."
وكم مرة استخدم فيها كلمة "نحن".
Never the word "I," and the word "we" 32 times.
لم تُستخدم كلمة "أنا" مطلقاً، بينما استُخدمت كلمة "نحن" 32 مرة.
He wasn't alone when he started.
لم يكون وحده عندما بدأ.
Nobody started a company alone. No one.
لا يؤسس أحد شركة بمفرده. لا أحد.
So we can create the community
لذا يمكننا أن ننشئ مجتمعاً حيث يكون فيه
where we have facilitators who come from a small business background
ميسرين يملكون خلفية بسيطة عن المشاريع التجارية
sitting in cafes, in bars, and your dedicated buddies
يجلسون في مقاهي وفي حانات، وأصدقائك المتفانين
who will do to you, what somebody did for this gentleman
الذين سيفعلون لك مافعله شخصٌ ما لهذا الرجل
who talks about this epic,
الذي تكلم عن هذه البطولة،
somebody who will say to you, "What do you need?
شخصٌ ما سيقول لك، "ماذا تحتاج؟"
What can you do? Can you make it?
ماذا يمكنك أن تفعل؟ هل يمكنك أن تصنع المنتج؟
Okay, can you sell it? Can you look after the money?"
حسناً، هل يمكنك بيع منتجك؟ هل يمكنك الحفاظ على مالك؟"
"Oh, no, I cannot do this.""Would you like me to find you somebody?"
"أوه, لا، لا يمكنني فعل ذلك." " هل تريد أن أجد لك من يساعدك؟"
We activate communities.
نحن نقوم بتفعيل المجتمعات.
We have groups of volunteers supporting the Enterprise Facilitator
نملك مجموعة من المتطوعين الذين يدعمون المؤسسة
to help you to find resources and people
ليساعدوك على إيجاد المصادر والأفراد
and we have discovered that the miracle
وقد اكتشفنا أن أعجوبة
of the intelligence of local people is such
ذكاء السكان المحليين هي
that you can change the culture and the economy
أنه بإمكانك تغيير ثقافة واقتصاد
of this community just by capturing the passion,
هذا المجتمع فقط بمجرد امتلاك شغف
the energy and imagination of your own people.
وطاقة ومخيلة أولئك الناس.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً (تصفيق)